下面几节我的目标是为大家展示
如果我们使用一个安全的PRG
My goal for the next few segments is to
show you that if we use a secure PRG, we'll
我们能得到一个安全的流密码
首先我们一定要定义
get a secure stream cipher. The first thing
we have to do is define is, what does it
流密码安全是什么意思呢？
无论何时我们定义安全
mean for a stream cipher to be secure? So
whenever we define security we always
我们总是从攻击者能干什么的角度来定义
define it in terms of what can the
attacker do? And what is the attacker
那么攻击者试图干什么？
记得在流密码中
trying to do? In the context of
stream ciphers remember these are only used
只使用一次性密钥，攻击者最多只能看到
with a onetime key, and as a result the
most the attacker is ever going to see is
使用密钥加密后的密文
just one cypher text encrypted using the
key that we're using. And so we're gonna
我们要限制攻击者获取密文的能力
limit the attackers ability to basically
obtain just one cypher text. And in
事实上稍后我们将允许攻击者做更多事情
fact later on we're going to allow the
attacker to do much, much, much more, but
但现在我们只给他密文。我们想找到
for now we're just gonna give him one
cypher text. And we wanted to find,
密码安全到底是什么意思？
那么第一个我们想到的定义
what does it mean for the cypher to
be secure? So the first definition that
就是，我们可以让攻击者
comes to mind is basically to say, well
maybe we wanna require that the attacker
无法还原密钥。好，给定密文
can't actually recover the secret key.
Okay so given ciphertext you
你应该是无法还原密钥的
但这是一个糟糕的定义
shouldn't be able to recover the secret
key. But that's a terrible definition
因为想想这个聪明但失败了的密码
because think about the falling brilliant
cipher but the way we encrypt the
我们使用密钥k，但直接输出明文作为密文
message using a key K is basically
we just output the message. Okay this
好的，这是一个聪明的密码，当然，
它没有做任何事情
is a brilliant cipher, yeah of course it
doesn't do anything given a message just
只是输出明文当作密文
这并不是一个好的加密
output a message as the cipher text.
This is not a particularly good encryption
不过，给定密文，可怜的攻击者
scheme; however, given the cipher text,
mainly the message the poor attacker
无法还原密钥，因为他不知道密钥
cannot recover the key because he doesn't
know what the key is. And so as a result
这个明显不安全的密码，
在这个要求下却是安全的
this cipher which clearly is insecure,
would be considered secure under this
所以这个定义不好
requirement for security. So this
definition will be no good. Okay so it's
不应从还原密钥的角度来定义安全
recovering the secret key is the wrong way
to define security. So the next thing we
那么我们接下来可以尝试的，
可能攻击者不在乎密钥
can kinda attempt is basically just say,
well maybe the attacker doesn't care about
他真正在乎的是明文
the secret key, what he really cares about
are the plain text. So maybe it should be
也许应该让攻击者难以还原整个明文
hard for the attacker to recover the
entire plain text. But even that doesn't
但甚至这点也没有用，因为想想如下加密
work because let's think about the
following encryption scheme. So suppose
假设这个加密取两个信息
what this encryption scheme does is it
takes two messages, so I'm gonna use two
我用双竖线来表示两个信息的联结
M0||M1表示联结M0和M1
lines to denote concatenation of two
messages M0 line, line M1 means
设想这个加密输出M0的明文
concatenate M0 and M1. And imagine
what the scheme does is really it outputs
再联结上M1的加密后的密文
M0 in the clear and concatenate to
that the encryption of M1. Perhaps even
可能使用了一次性密码本，怎么样？
这里攻击者掌握了密文
using the One Time Pad okay? And
so here the attacker is gonna be given one
他的目标是还原整个明文
cipher text. And his goal would be to
recover the entire plain texts. But the
但可怜的攻击者做不到，因为这里
我们可以用一次性密码本加密M1
poor attacker can't do that because here
maybe we've encrypted M1 using the One
这样攻击者无法还原M1
Time Pad so the attacker can't
actually recover M1 because we know the
因为只给密文的话，一次性密码本是安全的
One Time Pad is secure given just
one cipher text. So this construction
所以这个加密根据定义是安全的。
但是很不幸，这明显不是安全的加密
would satisfy the definition but
unfortunately clearly this is not a secure
因为我们泄漏了一半的明文内容
encryption scheme because we just leaked
half of the plain text. M0 is
攻击者完全知道M0，即使他
无法完全还原出明文
completely available to the attacker so
even though he can't recover all of the
他也能还原出大部分明文了
plain text he might be able to recover
most of the plain text, and that's clearly
这明显是不安全的。当然我们已经
知道了这个的解决方案
unsecured. So of course we already know
the solution to this and we talked about
我们讨论了香农的完美安全的定义
Shanon definition of security perfect
secrecy where Shannon's idea was that in
香农的想法是，当攻击者截获密文时
fact when the attacker intercepts a cipher
text he should learn absolutely no
他学不到任何关于明文的信息
他不应学到任何一点明文的内容
information about the plain texts. He
shouldn't even learn one bit about the
不仅学不到，他还不能够预测
plain text or even he shouldn't learn, he
shouldn't even be able to predict a little
明文中的任何一位，学不到任何关于明文的信息
bit about a bit of the plain text.
Absolutely no information about the plain text.
我们简要回顾一下香农完美安全的概念
So let's recall very briefly
Shannon's concept of perfect secrecy
我们说密码具备完美安全
basically we said that you know given a
cipher. We said the cipher has perfect
如果给两个相同长度的信息
密文的分布
secrecy if given two messages of the same
length it so happens that the distribution
如果我们随机选择密钥，然后我们看密文的分布
of cipher texts. Yet if we pick a random
key and we look into distribution of
我们加密M0，获得了与加密M1时严格相同的分布
cipher texts. We encrypt M0. We get
exactly the same distribution as when we
直观地，如果攻击者通过观察密文
encrypt M1. The intuition here was that if
the adversary observes the cipher texts
他是无法得知密文是来自哪一种分布的
then he doesn't know whether it came from
the distribution, the result of encrypting
是加密M0的，还是加密M1的
M0 or it came from the distribution as
the result of encrypting M1. And as a
于是他无法判断我们加密的是M0还是M1
result he can't tell whether we encrypted
M0 or M1. And that's true for all
这一点对所有等长的信息都成立。
可怜的攻击者无法得知
messages of the same length and as a
result a poor attacker doesn't really know
我们加密的是什么明文。当然
我们说了，从某种意义上
what message was encrypted. Of course we
already said that this definition is too
这个定义太强了，它需要很长的密钥
strong in the sense that it requires
really long keys if cipher has short
如果密钥太短，不可能满足这一定义
keys can't possibly satisfy this
definition. In a particular stream ciphers
特别地，流密码不可能满足这个定义。
好的，我们试图减弱这个定义
can't satisfy this definition. Okay so let's
try to weaken the definition a little bit
想到上节的内容，我们可以说
and let's think to the previous segment,
and we can say that instead of requiring
先不要求两个分布绝对相同，
我们可以要求
the two distributions to be absolutely
identical, what we can require is, is that
两个分布在计算上不可区分
two distributions just be computationally
indistinguishable. In other words a poor,
换句话说，高效但可怜的攻击者
无法区分这两个分布
efficient attacker cannot distinguish the
two distributions even though the
即使这些分布差别非常大
仅仅给一个分布的样本
distributions might be very, very, very
different. That just given a sample for
和另一分布的样本，攻击者无法区分
one distribution and a sample for another
distribution, the attacker can't tell which
他得到的样本来自哪一个分布
这个定义基本上是正确的
distribution he was given a sample from.
It turns out this definition is actually
但它还是有点太强了，无法被满足
almost right, but it's still a little too
strong, that still cannot be satisfied, so
所以我们不得不再加一条限制，
那就是不说这个定义
we have to add one more constraint, and
that is that instead of saying that this
对所有的M0和M1都成立
而是说只对攻击者
definition should have hold for all M0
and M1. It is to hold for only pairs M0 M1
能想到的明文(M0,M1)成立
that the attackers could
actually exhibit. Okay so this actually
好，这就引导我们来到语义安全的定义
leads us to the definition of semantics
security. And so, again this is semantics
这是一次性密码本的语义安全。
换句话说，攻击者只有密文
security for one time key. In other words
when the attacker is only given one cipher
我们定义语义安全的方式
是通过定义两个实验
text. And so the way we define semantic
security is by defining two experiments,
分别是实验0和实验1
okay we'll define experiment 0 and
experiment 1. And more generally we will
更一般地，我们把这些实验当作实验(B)
B可以是0或1
think of these as experiments parentheses
B, where B can be zero or one. Okay so the
好的，实验如下定义
有一攻击者试图破解加密系统
way the experiment is defined is as
follows, we have an adversary that's
攻击者A所做的，类似于
trying to break the system. An adversary
A, that's kinda the analog of statistical
对伪随机数发生器的统计测试
然后挑战者A这样做
tests in the world of pseudo random
generators. And then the challenger does
所以其实我们有两个挑战者
the following, so really we have two
challengers, but the challengers are so
但这两个挑战者很相似，所以我们可
把他们想象成一个挑战者
similar that we can just describe them as
a single challenger that in one case takes
一个情况下按方式0输出；
另一个情况下按方式1输出
his inputs bits set to zero, and the other
case takes his inputs bits set to
我来告诉大家这些挑战者是怎么做的
one. And let me show you what these
challengers do. The first thing the
首先，挑战者选取一个随机密钥
challenger is gonna do is it's gonna pick
a random key and then the adversary
然后攻击者输出两个信息M0和M1
basically is going to output two messages
M0 and M1. Okay so this is an explicit
好，这是一对信息
攻击者希望挑战之
pair of messages that the attacker wants
to be challenged on and as usual we're not
与往常一样，我们不试图隐藏信息长度
我们要求两个信息的长度一致
trying to hide the length of the messages,
we require that the messages be equal
然后挑战者输出M0的加密结果
length. And then the challenger basically
will output either the encryption of M0
或M1的加密结果。好
在实验0里挑战者会输出
or the encryption of M1, okay so in
experiment 0 the challenger will output
M0的加密，在实验1里
挑战者会输出M1的加密
the encryption of M0. In experiment 1
the challenger will output the encryption
好，这就是两个实验之间的差异
of M1. Okay so that the difference between
the two experiments. And then the
然后攻击者试图去猜
他得到的是M0的加密
adversary is trying to guess basically
whether he was given the encryption of M0
还是M1的加密。好的
这里引入一点记号
or given the encryption of M1. Okay so
here's a little bit of notation let's
我们定义事件Wb为在实验b中
攻击者输出1的所有事件
define the events Wb to be the events that
an experiment B the adversary output one.
所以W0中的事件意为
Okay so that is just an event that
basically in experiment zero W0 means that
在实验0中攻击者输出1
W1意为在实验1中输出1
the adversary output one and in experiment
one W1 means the adversary output one. And
我们可以定义攻击者的优势
now we can define the advantage of this
adversary, basically to say that this is
这就是攻击者A对加密机制E的
语义安全的优势
called the semantics security advantage of
the adversary A against the scheme E,
定义为两个事件概率的差距
to be the difference of the probability of
these two events. In other words we are
换句话说，我们看攻击者的行为
是否有所不同
looking at whether the adversary behaves
differently when he was given the
当给他M0的加密，和给他M1的加密
encryption of M0 from when he was given
the encryption of M1. And I wanna make
为确保这点讲清楚，我再说一遍
在实验0中
sure this is clear so I'm gonna say it one
more time. So in experiment zero he was
给攻击者M0的加密
在实验1中，给他M1的加密
given the encryption of M0 and in
experiment one he was given the encryption
现在我们对攻击者是否输出1感兴趣
of M1. Now we're just interested in
whether the adversary output 1 or not.
在这些实验中，如果在两个实验中
攻击者以同样的概率输出1
In these experiments. If in both
experiments the adversary output 1 with
就意味着攻击者无法区分两个实验
the same probability that means the
adversary wasn't able to distinguish the
实验0对攻击者而言
two experiments. Experiments zero
basically looks to the adversary the same
与实验1别无二致，因为两种情况
都以同样概率作出1的判断
as experiment one because in both cases
upload one with the same probability.
不过如果攻击者在两个实验中输出1
的概率非常不一样
However if the adversary is able to output
1 in one experiment with significantly
那么攻击者是可以
different probability than in the other
experiment, then the adversary was
区分两个实验的。好
actually able to distinguish the two
experiments. Okay so... To say this more
更形式化地，再次用优势来表达
因为优势是概率差
formally, essentially the advantage again
because it's the difference of two
优势在0和1之间
probabilities. The advantage is a number
between zero and one. If the advantage is
如果优势接近0，意味着攻击者无法
close to zero that means that the
adversary was not able to distinguish
区分实验0和实验1
但如果优势接近于1
experiment zero from experiment one.
However if the advantage is close to one,
意味着攻击者能很好地区分实验0
that means the adversary was very well
able to distinguish experiment zero from
和实验1，也就是他能很好地
experiment one and that really means that
he was able to distinguish an encryption
区分M0和M1的加密，对吧？
这就是语义安全的定义
of M0 from an encryption of M1, okay?
So that's out definition. Actually
实际上这就是优势的定义
that is just the definition of the
advantage and the definition is just what
这个定义也是大家所期望的
我们会谈到，一个对称加密机制
you would expect basically we'll say that
a symmetric encryption scheme is
是语义安全的，如果对于所有有效的
攻击者，这里要加上双引号
semantically secure if for all efficient
adversaries here I'll put these in quotes
“对所有有效攻击者，优势可忽略”
again, "For all efficient adversaries the
advantage is negligible." In other words,
换句话说，没有有效攻击者可以区分
M0和M1的加密
no efficient adversary can distinguish the
encryption of M0 from the encryption
这个定义反复在说
of M1 and basically this is what it
says repeatedly that for these two
对这两个攻击者能想到的明文
他也不能区分这两分布
messages that the adversary was able to
exhibit he wasn't able to distinguish
现在我想展示给大家
这是一个优雅的定义
these two distributions. Now I want to
show you this, this is actually a very
他可能不是很直观，但我想
elegant definition. It might not seem so
right away, but I want to show you some
给大家看这个定义的一些影响
大家会清楚地看到为何这么定义
implications of this definition and you'll
see exactly why the definition is the way
好的，我们看几个例子
第一个例子
it is. Okay so let's look at some
examples. So the first example is suppose
我们有个被破解的加密机制
换句话说，我们有攻击者A
we have a broken encryption scheme, in
other words suppose we have an adversary A
给定密文，他总能推断出
that somehow given the cipher text he is
always able to deduce the least
明文的最低位。好
那么给定明文M0的加密
significant bit of the plain text. Okay so
given the encryption of M0, this adversary
攻击者可以推断出M0的最低位
is able to deduce the least significant
bit of M0. So that is a terrible
那么这是个糟糕的加密机制，因为
其泄漏了明文的最低位
encryption scheme because it basically
leaks the least significant bit of the
给定密文的话。那么我想给大家看
plain text just given the cipher text. So
I want to show you that this scheme is
如果加密系统是语义安全的
therefore semantically secure so that kind
of shows that if a system is semantically
是不会有这样的攻击者的。好的
secure then there is no attacker of this
type. Okay so let's see why is the system
我们看为什么这个系统不是语义安全的
我们要利用这个攻击者
not semantically secure well so what we
are gonna do is we're gonna basically use
他可以学习到我们的最低位
our adversary who is able to learn our
most insignificant bits, we're going to
我们就利用他来破坏语义安全
我们来利用他来区分
use him to break semantic security so
we're going to use him to distinguish
实验0和实验1。好，我们这样做
experiment zero from experiment one. Okay
so here is what we are going to do. We are
我们是算法B，我们用算法B
algorithm B, we are going to be algorithm
B and this algorithm B is going to use
这个算法B里面用到了算法A
好，那么第一件发生的事当然是
algorithm A in its belly. Okay so the
first thing that is going to happen is of
挑战者选择一个随机密钥
course the challenger is going to choose a
random key. The first thing that is going
我们首先需要输出两个明文
to happen is that we need to output two
messages. The messages that we are going
我们要输出的两个明文有不同的最低位
to output basically are going to have
differently significant bits. So one
那么一个明文以0结尾
一个明文以1结尾
message is going to end with zero and one
message is going to end with one. Now what
挑战者干什么？挑战者将为我们
is the challenger going to do? The
challenger is going to give us the
加密M0或M1，这取决于是实验0或1
encryption of either M0 or M1,
depending on whether in experiment 0 or
然后我们就把得到的密文给攻击者
in experiment 1. And then we just
forward this cipher text to the adversary
现在攻击者A有什么特点？
okay so the adversary A. Now what is the
property of adversary A? Given the cipher
给定密文，攻击者A可以算出明文最低位
text, adversary A can tell us what the
least significant bits of the plain text is.
换句话说，攻击者会输出M0或M1的最低位
In other words the adversary is going
to output the least significant bits of M0 or M1
现在注意到那就是位B
but now behold that's
basically the bit B. And then we're just
然后我们输出我们的猜测，记为B'
going to output that as our guess so let's
call this thing B prime. Okay so now this
这就是语义安全攻击者的描述
现在大家告诉我
describes the semantic security adversary.
And now you tell me what is the semantic
这个攻击者的语义安全优势是多少？
我们看一下，在实验0中
security advantage of this adversary? Well
so let's see. In experiment zero, what is
攻击者B输出1的概率是多少？在实验0中
the probability that adversary B outputs
one? Well in experiment zero it is always
总是给定了M0，所以攻击者A
given the encryption of M zero and
therefore adversary A is always output the
总能输出M0的最低位，总是0
least significant bit of M zero which
always happens to be zero. In experiment
在实验0中，B总是输出0，
故以概率0输出1
zero, B always outputs zero. So the
probability that outputs one is zero.
但在实验1中，我们给定M1的加密
However in experiment one, we're given the
encryption of M1. So how likely is
那攻击者B输出1的可能性有多大？
它总是输出1
adversary B to output one in experiment
one? Well it always outputs one, again by
根据算法A的性质，优势为1
the properties of algorithm A and
therefore the advantage basically is one.
所以这是个巨大优势，就有这么大
So this is a huge advantage, it's as big
as it's gonna get. Which means that this
这意味着这个攻击者完全破解了这个系统
好，那么我们考虑在语义安全下
adversary completely broke the system.
Okay so we consider, so under semantic
能推导出最低位就足以完全破解系统
security basically just deducing the least
significant bits is enough to completely
这是根据语义安全的定义来的
break the system under a semantic security
definition. Okay, now the interesting
有趣的是，这当然不仅仅是最低位
thing here of course is that this is not
just about the least significant bit, in
事实上，比如明文的最高位
fact of the message for
example the most significant bit, you know
第七位。也许明文所有位的异或，等等
bit number seven. Maybe the XOR of
all the bits in the message and so on
任何一种信息，明文的任一位
and so forth any kind of information, any
bit about the plain text they can be
如果能被学习到，都意味着
系统不是语义安全的
learned basically would mean that the
system is not semantically secure. So
所以所有的攻击者想两个明文
basically all the adversary would have to
do would be to come up with two messages
M0和M1，一个他们能学到值0
M0 and M1 such that under one thing that
they learned it's the value zero and then
另一个能学到值1。比如说
如果A可以学到明文所有位的异或
the other thing, the value, is one. So for
example if A was able to learn the XOR
那么M0和M1所有位的异或可以不同
bits of the message, then M0
and M1 would just have different
这样一来攻击者A就可以
XOR for all the bits of their
messages and then this adversary A would
破解语义安全了。好
also be sufficient to break semantic
security. Okay so, basically for cipher
对于语义安全的密码，任一有效攻击者
is semantically secure then no
bit of information is revealed to an
都无法揭露明文的一丁点信息
这就完美安全的严格概念
efficient adversary. Okay so this is
exactly a concept of perfect secrecy only
只针对有效的攻击者，而不是所有攻击者
applied just efficient adversaries
rather than all adversaries. So the next
那么下面我想告诉大家，事实上
thing I wanna show you is that in fact the
one time pad in fact is
一次性密码本是语义安全的
它比语义安全还要好
semantically secure, they better be
semantically secure because it's in fact,
因为事实上它是完美安全的
那么我们来看看这是为什么
it's more than that it's perfectly secure.
So let's see why that's true. Well so
又是这些实验之一，那么设想
我们有一攻击者
again it's one of these experiments, so
suppose we have an adversary that claims
他声称破解了一次性密码本的语义安全
to break semantic security of the one time
pad. The first the adversary is gonna do
首先攻击者输出两个等长明文M0和M1
is he's gonna output two messages M0
and M1 of the same length.
他能得到什么挑战呢？作为挑战
他能得到M0或M1的加密
Now what does he get back as a challenge? As a
challenge, he gets either the encryption
用一次性密码本加密的
of M0 or the encryption of M1 under
the one time pad.
他试图区分这两个可能的密文，对吧？
And he's trying to distinguish between those
two possible cipher texts that he gets, right?
在实验0中，他获得了M0的加密
In experiment zero, he gets the encryption of
M0 and in experiment one, he gets the
在实验1中，他获得了M1的加密
我问大家，攻击者A对一次性密码本的
encryption of M1. Well so let me ask
you, so what is the advantage of adversary
优势是多少？我记得有些性质
A against the one time pad? So I
remember that the property of the ones I
告诉我K异或M0的分布
和K异或M1的分布是一样的
had is that, that K, XOR M0 is
distributed identically to K, XOR M1.
换句话说，这些分布是绝对同分布
In other words, these distributions are
absolutely identical distribution,
绝对同分布。这是异或的性质
如果我们把随机的密码本K
distributions, identical. This is a
property of XOR. If we XOR the random pad
和任何字符串异或，不管是M0还是M1
我们得到的一定是均匀分布
K with anything, either M0 or M1,
we get uniform distribution. So in both
那么两种情况下，算法A的输入
是严格的同分布
cases, algorithm A is given as in input
exactly the same distribution. Maybe the
也许是密文上的均匀分布
所以两种情况下攻击者表现一致
uniform distribution on cipher texts. And
therefore it's gonna behave exactly the
因为输入的分布是严格相等的
same in both cases because it was given
the exact distribution as input. And as a
于是，它的优势是0，意思是
一次性密码本是语义安全的
result, its advantage is zero, which means
that the onetime pad is semantically
现在有趣的是它不仅是语言安全的
secure. Now the interesting thing here is
not only is it semantically secure, it's
它对任何攻击者都是语义安全的
我们甚至不必限制
semantically secure for all adversaries.
We don't even have to restrict the
攻击者是有效的，无论多聪明
adversaries to be efficient. No adversary,
doesn't matter how smart you are, no
没有攻击者可以区分K异或M0和K异或M1
adversary will be able to distinguish
K XOR M0 from K XOR M1 because the two
因为它们同分布。好
所以一次性密码本是语义安全的
distributions are identical. Okay, so the
one time pad is semantically secure. Okay,
这就是我们的语义安全的定义
so that completes our definition of
semantic security so the next thing we're
下面我们要证明，事实上，
用安全PRG的流密码
going to do is prove to the secure PRG,
in fact implies that the stream cipher is
是语义安全的
semantically secure.